My my understanding of neurodiversity in
education, I always say it's it's it
means different things to different
people, you know, based on their kind of
unique set of experiences. So, I
wouldn't ever want to position myself as
the font of what that means in
educational sense, recognizing that lots
of different people engage and
experience neurodiversity in different
ways. But, for the purpose of the
research I do, I kind of define it,
broadly speaking, as a set of
intersecting factors around disability.
So, most namely and most commonly, this
is around kind of ADHD, dyspraxia,
dyslexia, and autism. And that isn't
exclusive just those things, there are
other aspects as well. But, for the
purpose of my research, I've always kind
of located it in those areas and looking
kind of for the in-between factors. But,
I do stress it's really important that
people experience neurodiversity in in
different ways. And so, I always kind of
what I want us to do is kind of have a
really fluid broad definition of this
because actually what we're beginning to
really come out of is this kind of
restrictive binary definition of
neurodiversity, which is I think has
even changed over the last 5 years,
never mind the last decade. So,
I think for me it's always this feeling
of
it's an evolving concept. Um, as the
needs of kind of pupils and learners
change, it's going to continue to
evolve. So, I think that's something
that we should always hold at the
forefront of our mind. Part of my
thinking around um neurodiversity,
particularly in terms of research, is
where we were,
where we are now, and where we're
looking to go. And a huge part of my
research focuses on how we bring all of
these kind of moving intersecting
elements together to provide better
outcomes for neurodivergent people. So,
one of the ways in which I've done this,
I've been fortunate to kind of engage in
research that has informed policy for
Welsh, Scottish, and um English
parliaments. And I guess one of the
things that's kind of really important
for me is really finding ways to make
the education curriculum, um more than
the national curriculum as we know it,
more inclusive.
And I guess part of that is really
interrogating what are some of the
things that exclude people from the
current curriculum in its current guys.
And I guess some of that relation
or it kind of arcs back to my own
experiences as a child who was obviously
part of the national curriculum in some
way and going to school
and feeling I guess ostracized in some
ways and I couldn't really make sense of
that experience because a lot of the
mechanisms or pedagogical mechanisms
that were used to engage
learners at that time was a kind of one
glove fits all model and I've always
kind of really strongly been against
that. And it's one of the things that
motivated me to become a teacher in the
first place. It's also one of the things
that motivated me to become an academic
and engaging in the practice element of
this work which kind of presents the
theories around this and the kind of and
the data and then practice element in
terms of how to work with educational
stakeholders and parliamentarians
to ensure that we kind of really create
as an inclusive a space as possible for
neurodivergent
individuals but not just neurodivergent
individuals, all pupils and stakeholders
within the education system. So my
present research focuses on a project
I'm working with my colleague and best
friend Dr. Chantel Lewis who is at the
University of Oxford and our book really
focuses on how we bring love, compassion
and empathy into learning spaces but
particularly for neurodivergent
children. And I think one thing that's
really important to kind of
illustrate is that Chantel herself
identifies as neurodivergent as someone
who has ADHD, dyslexia and dyspraxia. So
both of our experiences and my
experiences as an autistic person kind
of really amalgamate to kind of make
some sense of not only our own
experiences in the education system as
neurodivergent people but people who
presently reside in the education system
and what their experiences have been
like and how we can use I guess
political levers, educational levers and
beyond to really think about how we
change the learning space for
neurodivergent people, not just within
the education system, but society more
broadly.
One of the things that would
surprise people um that they might not
be aware of is actually the amount of
interventions Cambridge has in place
support neurodivergent learners. And I
think that has been I've been here just
over a year, and that's been one of the
things that has hugely surprised me.
There are so many interventions and so
many actually inclusive ways in which
adaptations are made for neurodivergent
people. And what I would encourage all
institutions to do, as well as
Cambridge, is to continue to kind of
build upon that success and support
neurodivergent learners
in these kind of really innovative,
supportive ways, using the resource and
democratizing that as far and as wide as
possible. I think Cambridge has done
that
at least for the year that I've been
here anyway exceptionally well from what
I've observed, and I believe it was
happening way before I arrived here
anyway.